Prepare for an unforgettable trip.
Luca is a animation, comedy, fantasy film directed by Enrico Casarosa.
Luca and his best friend Alberto experience an
unforgettable summer on the Italian Riviera.
But all the fun is threatened by a deeply-held secret: they are sea
monsters from another world just below the water’s surface.
Luca Paguro (voice), played by Jacob Tremblay.
Alberto Scorfano (voice), played by Jack Dylan Grazer.
Giulia Marcovaldo (voice), played by Emma Berman.
Ercole Visconti (voice), played by Saverio Raimondo.
Daniela Paguro (voice), played by Maya Rudolph.
Massimo Marcovaldo (voice), played by Marco Barricelli.
Luca is a 2021 American animated fantasy film produced by
Pixar Animation Studios for Walt Disney Pictures.
The film was directed by Enrico Casarosa, produced by Andrea Warren and written by Jesse Andrews
and Mike Jones from a story developed by Casarosa, Andrews, and Simon Stephenson.
It stars the voices of Jacob Tremblay, Jack Dylan Grazer, Emma Berman, Saverio
Raimondo, Maya Rudolph, Marco Barricelli, and Jim Gaffigan.
The film is set on the Italian Riviera in the 1950s, and centers on Luca Paguro (Tremblay), a young sea monster boy with the ability to assume human form while on land, who
explores the town of Portorosso with his new best friends, Alberto Scorfano (Grazer) and Giulia Marcovaldo (Berman), experiencing a life-changing summer adventure.
Luca draws inspiration from Casarosa's childhood in Genoa, Italy.
Several Pixar artists were sent to the Italian Riviera gathering research from
Italian culture and environment to create Portorosso, the primary setting.
The sea monsters, a "metaphor for feeling different", were loosely
based on old Italian regional myths and folklore.
As with the short film La Luna (2011), the design and animation were inspired
by hand-drawn and stop motion works and Hayao Miyazaki's style.
Casarosa described the result as a film that "pays homage to Federico Fellini and other
classic Italian filmmakers, with a dash of Miyazaki in the mix too".
Development on Luca lasted for five years, with production
being done remotely during the COVID-19 pandemic.
Dan Romer composed the film's musical score.
Luca premiered at the Aquarium of Genoa on June 13, 2021, and was released direct-to-streaming on
Disney+ in the United States on June 18, 2021 in response to the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.
It was released in theaters in countries without the streaming service, and given a simultaneous
one-week theatrical run at Hollywood's El Capitan Theatre, from June 18 to 24, 2021.
It was theatrically released in the United States on March 22, 2024.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, and was the most-viewed
streaming film of 2021, with over 10.6 billion minutes watched.
It was nominated for Best Animated Feature Film at the 79th
Golden Globe Awards and the 94th Academy Awards.
A short film, Ciao Alberto, was released on Disney+ on November 12, 2021.
The film explores themes of friendship, monster, italy, villain, coming of age.
The tone is lighthearted and thought_provoking.